My name is Ursus Wehrli, and I would like to talk to you this morning
اسمي أورسوس فيرلي، وأود أن أتحدث إليكم اليوم
about my project, Tidying Up Art.
عن مشروعي، ترتيب الفن
First of all -- any questions so far?
في البداية -- هل لديكم الأسئلة في ما قلته إلى الآن؟
First of all, I have to say I'm not from around here.
في البداية يجب أن أقول إنني لست من هنا
I'm from a completely different cultural area, maybe you noticed?
أنا من منطقة ثقافية مختلفة تمامًا، ربما قد لاحظتم؟
I mean, I'm wearing a tie, first. And then secondly, I'm a little bit nervous
فأنا أرتدي رباطة عنق، أولا. ثانيًا، أنا متوتر بعض الشيء
because I'm speaking in a foreign language,
لأن أتكلم بلغة أجنبية
and I want to apologize in advance, for any mistakes I might make.
وأود أن أعتذر مقدمًا عن أي أخطاء قد أقع فيها، لأنني من سويسرا
Because I'm from Switzerland, and I just don't hope you think this is Swiss German
وآمل فقط ألا تعقتدوا بأني أتكلم الآن الآن هي اللهجة السويسرية للغة الألمانية
I'm speaking now here. This is just what it sounds like
بل هذه هي الطريقة
if we Swiss try to speak American.
التي نتحدث بها كسويسريين اللغة الإنجليزية
But don't worry -- I don't have trouble with English, as such.
. لكن لا تقلقوا -- فأنا ليس لدي مشكلة في التحدث باللغة الإنجليزية بهذه الطريقة.
I mean, it's not my problem, it's your language after all.
فهي ليست مشكلتي، لأنها لغتكم في نهاية الأمر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I am fine. After this presentation here at TED, I can simply go back to Switzerland,
ليس لدي مشكلة. فبعد هذه الندوة هنا في تيد، أستطيع أن أرجع إلى سويسرا
and you have to go on talking like this all the time.
ويظل عليكم أن تستمروا في التحدث بهذه الطريقة طول الوقت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I've been asked by the organizers to read from my book.
طلب مني المنظمون أن أقرأ من كتابي
It's called "Tidying Up Art" and it's, as you can see,
عنوانه "تايدينج أب آرت" (ترتيب الفن)، وهو، كما بإمكانكم أن ترون
it's more or less a picture book.
كتاب صور تقريبًا
So the reading would be over very quickly.
لذلك فقد نفرغ من قراءته بسرعة
But since I'm here at TED, I decided to hold my talk here in a more modern way,
ولكن حيث إنني هنا في تيد، قررت أن أقدم حديثي هنا بطريقة أكثر حداثة
in the spirit of TED here, and I managed to do some slides here for you.
و من محيا أجواء تيد، أعددت لكم بعض شرائح العرض هنا
I'd like to show them around so we can just, you know --
أود أن أعرضها عليكم كي، تعرفون --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Actually, I managed to prepare for you some enlarged pictures -- even better.
في الواقع، لقد أعددت لكم هنا صورة مكبرة -- أفضل.
So Tidying Up Art, I mean, I have to say, that's a relatively new term.
فإذًا "تايدينج أب آرت"، أعني، علي أن أقول إنه مصطلح جديد نسبيا
You won't be familiar with it.
لا أتوقع أن تكونوا عالمين به
I mean, it's a hobby of mine that I've been indulging in for the last few years,
أعني، إنه من هواياتي التي كنت أمارسها في السنوات الأخيرة الماضية
and it all started out with this picture of the American artist, Donald Baechler
وقد بدأ الأمر بهذه اللوحة التي رسمها الفنان الأمريكي، دونالد بيشلير
I had hanging at home. I had to look at it every day
وكانت معلقة في بيتي. وكان علي أن أنظر إليها كل يوم
and after a while I just couldn't stand the mess anymore
وبعد فترة لم أعد أستطع تحمل الفوضى
this guy was looking at all day long.
التي كان ينظر إليها الشاب طول اليوم
Yeah, I kind of felt sorry for him.
نعم، شعرت بشيء من الأسى تجاهه
And it seemed to me even he felt really bad
وبدا لي أن شعر بالأسى
facing these unorganized red squares day after day.
لأنه يواجه هذه المربعات الحمراء غير المنظمة كل يوم
So I decided to give him a little support,
لذلك قررت أن أعطيه بعض الدعم
and brought some order into neatly stacking the blocks on top of each other.
وأوجدت شيءً من النظام بأن وضعت المربعات بشكل منظم فوق بعضها البعض
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah. And I think he looks now less miserable.
نعم، وأعتقد أنه يبدو الآن أقل معاناة
And it was great. With this experience, I started to look more closely
وكانت تجربة عظيمة. وبهذه التجربة، بدأت أنظر بشكل أدق
at modern art. Then I realized how, you know, the world of modern art
إلى الفن الحديث ثم أدركت كم، أي، أن عالم الفن الحديث
is particularly topsy-turvy.
في فوضى كبيرة
And I can show here a very good example.
وأستطيع أن أريكم مثالا جيدًا جدًا
It's actually a simple one, but it's a good one to start with.
إنه في الحقيقة بسيط جدًا، ولكن جيد كبداية
It's a picture by Paul Klee.
إنها لوحة للفنان بول لي،
And we can see here very clearly, it's a confusion of color.
وبإمكاننا أن نرى هنا بمنتهى الوضوح أنها عبارة عن تداخل للألوان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah. The artist doesn't really seem to know where to put the different colors.
نعم. فلا يبدو أن الفنان يعرف أين يضع الألوان المختلفة
The various pictures here of the various elements of the picture --
الصور المختلفة هنا للعناصر المختلفة للوحة --
the whole thing is unstructured.
اللوحة بأكملها غير مرتبة
We don't know, maybe Mr. Klee was probably in a hurry, I mean --
ولا نعرف، ربما كان السيد لي على عجل، أعني --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- maybe he had to catch a plane, or something.
-- ربما كان عليه اللحاق بطائرة، أو ما شابه
We can see here he started out with orange,
نستطيع هنا أن نرى أنه بدأ باللون البرتقالي
and then he already ran out of orange,
ثم نفد من عنده اللون البرتقالي
and here we can see he decided to take a break for a square.
ونستطيع أن نرى هنا أنه قرر أن يأخذ استراحة في هذا المربع
And I would like to show you here my tidied up version of this picture.
وأود أن أعرض عليكم هنا نسختي المرتبة لهذه اللوحة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We can see now what was barely recognizable in the original:
بإمكاننا أن نرى ما كان بالكاد يمكن تمييزه في اللوحة الأصلية:
17 red and orange squares are juxtaposed with just two green squares.
17 مربعًا أحمرًا وبرتقاليًا موضوعين في غير اتساق بجانب مربعين خضر
Yeah, that's great.
نعم، إنه أمر عظيم
So I mean, that's just tidying up for beginners.
لذا أعني، هذا ترتيب للمبتدئين
I would like to show you here a picture which is a bit more advanced.
أود أن تروا لوحة من مستوى أكثر تقدما
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What can you say? What a mess.
ماذا بإمكانكم أن تقولوا؟ يا لها من فوضى
I mean, you see, everything seems to have been scattered aimlessly around the space.
أعني، ترون أن كل شيء يبدو أنه بعثر دون هدف في جميع الأنحاء
If my room back home had looked like this,
إذا كانت غرفتي في منزلي بهذا الشكل
my mother would have grounded me for three days.
لكانت أمي حبستني ثلاثة أيام
So I'd like to -- I wanted to reintroduce some structure into that picture.
لذا أود -- أود أن أعيد النظام في هذه اللوحة
And that's really advanced tidying up.
وهذا بحق الترتيب المتقدم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Yeah, you're right. Sometimes people clap at this point,
نعم، أنتم على حق. بعض الناس يصفقون في هذا الموضع
but that's actually more in Switzerland.
ولكن التصفيق أكثر من ذلك في سويسرا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We Swiss are famous for chocolate and cheese. Our trains run on time.
نحن السويسريون مشهورون بالشوكولاتة والجبن. قطاراتنا منضبطة في مواعيدها
We are only happy when things are in order.
ولا نكون سعداء إلى عندما تكون الأمور منظمة
But to go on, here is a very good example to see.
ولكن استمرارًا لموضوعي، هذا مثال جيد جدًا
This is a picture by Joan Miro.
إنها لوحة للفنان جوان ميرو
And yeah, we can see the artist has drawn a few lines and shapes
ونعم، بإمكاننا أن نرى أن الفنان قد رسم بعض الخطوط والأشكال
and dropped them any old way onto a yellow background.
وألقاها كيفما اتفق على خلفية صفراء
And yeah, it's the sort of thing you produce when you're doodling on the phone.
ونعم، اللوحة تبدو مثل الرسومات التي نرسمها ونحن نتحدث في الهاتف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this is my --
وهذه --
-- you can see now the whole thing takes up far less space.
-- بإمكانكم أن ترون الآن أن اللوحة بأكملها تستغل فضاءً أقل بكثر
It's more economical and also more efficient.
وهي اقتصادية أكثر وأكثر كفاءةً
With this method Mr. Miro could have saved canvas for another picture.
بهذا الأسلوب، بإمكان السيد ميرو أن يوفر لوحًا بيضاء ليرسم عليها لوحة أخرى
But I can see in your faces that you're still a little bit skeptical.
ولكني أستطيع أن أرى في وجوهكم أنه ما زال يخامركم الشك
So that you can just appreciate how serious I am about all this,
ولكي تدركوا كم أن جاد في هذا الموضوع
I brought along the patents, the specifications for some of these works,
أحضرت لكم براءات الاختراع، ومواصفات بعض هذه الأعمال
because I've had my working methods patented
لأني قد حصلت على براءات اختراع لأساليب العمل الخاصة بي
at the Eidgenössische Amt für Geistiges Eigentum in Bern, Switzerland.
في أيدجينوسيشى أمت فيور جايستيشيس في برن، سويسرا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'll just quote from the specification.
سأقرأ اقتباسًا من المواصفات
"Laut den Kunstprüfer Dr. Albrecht --"
"لاوت دين كونستبروفر د. ألبرشت -- (كلام باللغة الألمانية)"
It's not finished yet.
لم ينتهِ بعد
"Laut den Kunstprüfer Dr. Albrecht Götz von Ohlenhusen
"لاوت دين كونستبريوفر د. ألبريشت جوتس فون أولينهوزين
wird die Verfahrensweise rechtlich geschützt welche die Kunst
فيرد دي فيرفارينفايسى ريشتليش جيزوتست فيلشى دي كونست
durch spezifisch aufgeräumte Regelmässigkeiten
دورش سبيتيفيش أوفجيرويمتى ريجيلمايسيجكايتين
des allgemeinen Formenschatzes
ديس أللجيماينين فورمينشاتسيس
neue Wirkungen zu erzielen möglich wird."
نويى فيركونجين تسو إرتسيلين ميوجليش فيرد" (كلام باللغة الألمانية)"
Ja, well I could have translated that, but you would have been none the wiser.
نعم، كان بإمكاني أن أترجم ذلك، ولكن لم تكونوا لتفهموا أكثر
I'm not sure myself what it means but it sounds good anyway.
لست متأكدًا من معنى ذلك ولكنه يبدو جيدًا على أي حال
I just realized it's important how one introduces new ideas to people,
لقد أدركت كم هو مهم أن يقدم الإنسان أفكارًا جديدة للناس
that's why these patents are sometimes necessary.
ولهذا فبراءة الاختراع هذه هي في بعض الأحيان ضرورية
I would like to do a short test with you.
أود أن أقوم باختبار صغير معكم
Everyone is sitting in quite an orderly fashion here this morning.
الجميع جالسون بطريقة مرتبة جدًا هنا اليوم
So I would like to ask you all to raise your right hand. Yeah.
لذا، أود أن أطلب منكم أن ترفعوا أيديكم اليمنى، نعم
The right hand is the one we write with, apart from the left-handers.
اليد اليمنى التي نكتب بها، باستثناء العسر
And now, I'll count to three. I mean, it still looks very orderly to me.
والآن، سأعد إلى ثلاثة. أعني، يبدو لي أنكم لا تزالون منظمين
Now, I'll count to three, and on the count of three
والآن سأعد إلى ثلاثة، وعند رقم ثلاثة
I'd like you all to shake hands with the person behind you. OK?
أريد منكم أن تصافحوا الشخص الجالس خلفكم. حسن؟
One, two, three.
واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can see now, that's a good example: even behaving in an orderly, systematic way
ترون الآن، هذا مثال جيد: فحتى التصرف بطريقة منظمة
can sometimes lead to complete chaos.
قد يؤدي إلى فوضى عارمة
So we can also see that very clearly in this next painting.
ونستطيع أن نرى ذلك بوضوح شديد في اللوحة التالية
This is a painting by the artist, Niki de Saint Phalle.
هي لوحة للفنان نيكي دو سان فال
And I mean, in the original it's completely unclear to see
أعني، في اللوحة الأصلية، لا يتضح أبدًا
what this tangle of colors and shapes is supposed to depict.
عن ماذا يعبر مثلث الألوان والأشكال هذا
But in the tidied up version, it's plain to see that it's a sunburnt woman playing volleyball.
ولكن في النسخة المرتبة، يتضح جليًا أنها امرأة أحرقتها الشمس أثناء لعبها للكرة الطائرة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, it's a -- this one here, that's much better.
نعم، إنه -- هذه اللوحة هنا، إنها أفضل بكثير
That's a picture by Keith Haring.
إنها لوحة للفنان كيث هايرينج
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I think it doesn't matter.
أعتقد أن ذلك لا يهم
So, I mean, this picture has not even got a proper title.
لذا، أعني، هذه اللوحة ليس لها حتى عنوان مناسب
It's called "Untitled" and I think that's appropriate.
فعنوانها "بلا عنوان" وأظن أن ذلك مناسب
So, in the tidied-up version we have a sort of Keith Haring spare parts shop.
وفي النسخة المرتبة، لدينا ما يشبه محل قطاع غيار لكيث هايرينج
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is Keith Haring looked at statistically.
هذا كيث هايرينج في صورة إحصاءات
One can see here quite clearly,
يمكننا أن نرى هنا بوضوح
you can see we have 25 pale green elements,
تستطيعون أن ترون 25 عنصرًا أخضرًا شاحبًا
of which one is in the form of a circle.
أحدها على شكل دائرة
Or here, for example, we have 27 pink squares with only one pink curve.
أو هنا، مثلا، لدينا 27 مربعًا ورديًا ومنحنى وردي واحد فقط
I mean, that's interesting. One could extend this sort of statistical analysis
أعني، إن هذا مثير للاهتمام. وقد نستطيع تطبيق هذا التحليل الإحصائي
to cover all Mr. Haring's various works,
على جميع أعمال السيد هايرينج المختلفة
in order to establish in which period the artist favored pale green circles or pink squares.
كي نحدد في أي عصر فضل الفنان الدوائر الخضراء الشاحبة أو المربعات الوردية
And the artist himself could also benefit from this sort of listing procedure
وقد يستفيد الفنان نفسه من طريقة إعداد القوائم هذه
by using it to estimate how many pots of paint he's likely to need in the future.
بأن يستخدمها ليتوقع كم علبة طلاء سيحتاج في المستقبل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
One can obviously also make combinations.
يمكننا كذلك بالطبع أن نقوم بعمليات تجميع
For example, with the Keith Haring circles and Kandinsky's dots.
مثلا، بدوائر كيث هايرينج ونقاط كاندينسكي
You can add them to all the squares of Paul Klee.
بإمكانكم أن تضيفوها إلى مربعات بول لي
In the end, one has a list with which one then can arrange.
في النهاية، يكون لدينا قائمة نستطيع الترتيب بالاستناد إليها
Then you categorize it, then you file it, put that file in a filing cabinet,
ثم تصنفونها، وتضعونها في ملف، وتضعون الملف في خزانة ملفات
put it in your office and you can make a living doing it.
وتضعونها في مكاتبكم، وتستطيع التكسب من فعل ذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, from my own experience. So I'm --
نعم، بناء على تجربتي الشخصية فأنا إذًا --
Actually, I mean, here we have some artists that are a bit more structured. It's not too bad.
في الواقع، أعني، هناك فنانون أكثر تنظيما. ليس الأمر سيئاً للغاية
This is Jasper Johns. We can see here he was practicing with his ruler.
هذا جاسبر جونز. نرى هنا أنه كان يتدرب على استخدام المسطرة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I think it could still benefit from more discipline.
لكني أعتقد أن اللوحة قد تحتاج إلى شيء من الانضباط
And I think the whole thing adds up much better if you do it like this.
وأظن أن اللوحة بأكملها تبدو منطقية أكثر إذا بدت هكذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And here, that's one of my favorites.
وهنا، هذا من الأمور التي أفضلها
Tidying up Rene Magritte -- this is really fun.
ترتيب لوحات ريني ماجريت -- إن ذلك ممتع للغاية
You know, there is a --
تعرفون، هناك --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm always being asked what inspired me to embark on all this.
لقد سُئلت ما الذي ألهمني أن أبدأ في كل هذا
It goes back to a time when I was very often staying in hotels.
يرجع الأمر إلى زمن كنت فيه أبيت في الفنادق كثيرا
So once I had the opportunity to stay in a ritzy, five-star hotel.
وذات مرة حظيت بفرصة لأن أبيت في فندق فخم وخمس نجوم
And you know, there you had this little sign --
وتعرفون، كانت هناك هذه العلامة الصغيرة --
I put this little sign outside the door every morning that read,
وضعت علامة صغيرة خارج الباب كل صباح تقول
"Please tidy room." I don't know if you have them over here.
"لطفًا رتب الغرفة". لا أعرف إن كانت معي هنا
So actually, my room there hasn't been tidied once daily, but three times a day.
في الواقع، غرفتي في هذا الفندق لم تكن ترتب مرة في اليوم، بل ثلاث مرات
So after a while I decided to have a little fun,
لذلك فبعد فترة، قررت أن أقوم بأمر ممتع
and before leaving the room each day I'd scatter a few things around the space.
فكنت قبل مغادرة الغرفة كل يوم أبعثر بعض الأشياء في أنحاء الغرفة
Like books, clothes, toothbrush, etc. And it was great.
مثل كتب، وملابس، وفرشاة أسنان، وما إلى ذلك. وكان الأمر رائعا
By the time I returned everything had always been neatly returned to its place.
وعند عودتي، كنت أجد كل شيء قد أعيد إلى مكانه بشكل منظم
But then one morning, I hang the same little sign onto that picture by Vincent van Gogh.
ولكن في صباح يوم ما، علقت نفس العلامة الصغيرة على لوحة للفنان فنسينت فان جوخ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you have to say this room hadn't been tidied up since 1888.
وبإمكانكم أن تقولون إن هذه الغرفة لم ترتب منذ عام 1888
And when I returned it looked like this.
وعندما عدت وجدتها هكذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, at least it is now possible to do some vacuuming.
نعم، على الأقل يمكن الآن أن ننظف بالمكنسة
OK, I mean, I can see there are always people
حسن، أعني، أستطيع أن أرى أن هناك دائمًا أناس
that like reacting that one or another picture
يحبون أن يروا أن لوحة أو أخرى
hasn't been properly tidied up. So we can make a short test with you.
لم ترتب بشكل صحيح. لذا، أستطيع أن أجري اختبارًا صغيرًا معكم
This is a picture by Rene Magritte,
هذه لوحة للفنان ريني ماجريت
and I'd like you all to inwardly -- like in your head, that is --
وأريد منكم جميعًا، بداخلكم، أي في أذهانكم،
to tidy that up. So it's possible that some of you would make it like this.
أن ترتبوها. يحتمل أن يجعلها بعضكم تبدو هكذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah? I would actually prefer to do it more this way.
صحيح؟ ولكني أفضل أن أرتبها بهذه الطريقة
Some people would make apple pie out of it.
بعض الناس سيجعلونها تبدو مثل فطيرة تفاح
But it's a very good example to see that the whole work
ولكنها مثال جيد لنرى أن العمل بأكمله
was more of a handicraft endeavor that involved the very time-consuming job
كان عبارة عن محاولة حرفية احتاجت إلى عمل يستهلك وقتًا كبيرًا
of cutting out the various elements and sticking them back in new arrangements.
وهو تقطيع العناصر المختلفة وإعادة لصقها في ترتيبات جديدة
And it's not done, as many people imagine, with the computer,
ولا يتم ذلك، كما يتخيل بعض الناس، باستخدام الحاسب الآلي
otherwise it would look like this.
وإلا كانت لتبدو هكذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So now I've been able to tidy up pictures that I've wanted to tidy up for a long time.
لذا، فالآن قد استطعت أن أرتب اللوح التي رغبت في ترتيبها لوقت طويل
Here is a very good example. Take Jackson Pollock, for example.
وهذا مثال جيد جدًا. انظروا مثلا إلى الفنان جاكسون بولوك
It's -- oh, no, it's -- that's a really hard one.
إنها، لا، إنها لوحة صعبة للغاية
But after a while, I just decided here to go all the way
ولكن بعد مدة،
and put the paint back into the cans.
قررت أن أعيد الدهان إلى العلب
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Or you could go into three-dimensional art.
أو قد تستطيعون النظر إلى الفن الثلاثي الأبعاد
Here we have the fur cup by Meret Oppenheim.
لدينا هنا لوحة "فور كاب" للفنانة ميريت أوبينهايم
Here I just brought it back to its original state.
هنا أرجعتها إلى حالتها الأصلية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But yeah, and it's great, you can even go, you know --
ولكن نعم، وهي رائعة، وبإمكانكم كذلك، تعرفون --
Or we have this pointillist movement for those of you who are into art.
أو لدينا هذه الحركة النقطية، للمهتمين منكم بالفن
The pointillist movement is that kind of paintings
الحركة النقطية شيء هي نوع من اللوحات
where everything is broken down into dots and pixels.
حيث يكسر كل شيء إلى نقاط ومربعات صغيرة،
And then I -- this sort of thing is ideal for tidying up.
لذا فقد -- هذا النوع من الفن مناسب جدًا للترتيب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I once applied myself to the work of the inventor of that method, Georges Seurat,
ذات مرة، طبقت أسلوبي على عمل مخترع هذا المنهج، جورج سوراه
and I collected together all his dots.
وجمعت جميع نقطه
And now they're all in here.
وهي كلها هنا الآن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can count them afterwards, if you like.
يمكنكم أن تعدوها لاحقًا إن أردتم
You see, that's the wonderful thing about the tidy up art idea:
ترون، إن هذا هو الشيء الرائع بخصوص فكرة ترتيب الفن:
it's new. So there is no existing tradition in it.
إنه جديد. لذا، فلا يوجد له تقاليد ثابتة
There is no textbooks, I mean, not yet, anyway.
ليست هناك كتب تعليمية، أعني، ليس بعد، على أي حال
I mean, it's "the future we will create."
أعني، إنها "المستقبل الذي سنبنيه".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But to round things up I would like to show you just one more.
ولكن لتقريب الأمر، أود أن أريكم لوحة أخرى واحدة فقط
This is the village square by Pieter Bruegel.
هذا ميدان القرية للفنان بيتر بروجل
That's how it looks like when you send everyone home.
هذا شكلها عندما تعيد كل الناس إلى منازلهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, maybe you're asking yourselves
نعم، ربما تسألون أنفسكم
where old Bruegel's people went?
أين ذهب الناس القدماء الذين رسمهم بروجل؟
Of course, they're not gone. They're all here.
بالطبع لم يرحلوا. إنهم كلهم هنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I just piled them up.
لقد جمعتهم فوق بعضهم البعض
So I'm -- yeah, actually I'm kind of finished at that moment.
لذا أنا، نعم، في الواقع، لقد انتهيت الآن
And for those who want to see more, I've got my book downstairs in the bookshop.
ولمن يريد رؤية المزيد، فكتابي موجود في المكتبة بالأسفل
And I'm happy to sign it for you with any name of any artist.
وأسعد بأن أوقعه لكم باسم أي فنان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But before leaving I would like to show you,
ولكن قبل أن أغادر، أود أن أريكم
I'm working right now on another -- in a related field
أنا أعمل الآن على -- في مجال ذي علاقة
with my tidying up art method. I'm working in a related field.
بأسلوب ترتيب الفن. أعمل في مجال ذي علاقة
And I started to bring some order into some flags.
وبدأت في إحداث بعض النظام في بعض الأعلام
Here -- that's just my new proposal here for the Union Jack.
هنا -- هذا اقتراحي الجديد للعلم البريطاني
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then maybe before I leave you ...
وربما قبل أن أترككم --
yeah, I think, after you have seen that I have to leave anyway.
نعم، أظن أنه بعد أن رأيتم هذا يجب علي المغادرة على أي حال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, that was a hard one. I couldn't find a way to tidy that up properly,
نعم، لقد كان الأمر شاقا. لم أستطع إيجاد طريقة لأرتب ذلك بطريقة مناسبة
so I just decided to make it a little bit more simpler.
لذا قررت أن أجعله أكثر بساطة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)